A Finding Aid to the Stanton Macdonald-Wright Papers, 1890-2008, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Writings, 1913-2003; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 4.7 Linear feet Boxes 3-7
  - "The Continuing Role of Stanton MacDonald-Wright and Synchronism in Modern Painting" by Elizabeth Hertz, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
- Diaries, 1909-1991; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 7-9
  Diaries consist of a number of diaries and travel journals. One diary was written in Paris in 1909 in which Macdonald-Wright muses over the aesthetics of art and his color theories. Five additional disbound diaries cover his life from 1939-1973. Travel diaries date from 1959-1972 and cover trips to Italy, Japan, and Hawaii.
  - Paris Diary, 1909-1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 28-29)
  - Hawaii and Japan Travel Diary, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 31-32)
  - Hawaii and Japan Travel Diary, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Japan Travel Diaries, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 34-36)
  - Japan and Los Angeles Trip Diaries, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Hawaii and Japan Travel Diary, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Italy Travel Diary, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - France, Italy, and England Travel Diary, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Italy and London Travel Diary, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - France and Italy Travel Diary, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Hawaii Travel Diary, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
  - Diary Entry Typescript, circa 1909; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Diary Entry, Europe, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Diary Entry Excerpt, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1939-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 16-23)
  - Disbound Diary 2, 1957-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 24-28)
  - Disbound Diary 3, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 29-32)
  - Disbound Diary 4, 1963-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 33-38)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1968-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 39-49)
  - Jean Macdonald-Wright Diary, 1981-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Jean Macdonald-Wright Diary, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Personal Business Records, 1946-2006; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 9-10
  Personal business records consists of inventory cards and lists, invoices, property records, and legal documents related to the Macdonald-Wright estate. Also included are files between the estate and various galleries, such as the Esther Robles Gallery and the Goldfield Galleries, in regards to donations of works of art during both his active career and by his estate in the years after his death.
  - Inventory Cards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2-5)
  - Inventories and Price Lists, 1969-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6-10)
  - Invoices and Receipts, 1953-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11-15)
  - Estate Correspondence, 2004-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Jean's Family, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Veronica Sommer, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Joseph Chowning Gallery, 1980-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19-24)
  - Brown & Brown/Orbach & Hoff, 1974-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 25-32)
  - Robert Schaap, 1992-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 33-34)
  - Tuttle & Taylor, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Sulmeyer & Kupetz, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Fogel, McInery, Dealey, & McCall, 1973-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Legal Correspondence, 1989, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Legal and Estate Records, 1993-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Insurance, 1973-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Income from Estate and Art Sales, 2002-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Sales Records, 1973-1979, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
  - Estate Records, Sutton Family, 1946, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Property Records, 1944-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Gift to Tokyo University Library, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Taniguchi Shoten, 1953-1954, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
  - Gift of "Piscine" by Morgan Russell to Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14-15)
  - Esther Robles Gallery, 1958, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Goldfield Galleries, 1968, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Art Appraisal, Asian Art, 1969-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - La Tortue Galerie, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Condition Report, Seated Man Synchromy, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Harmon Gallery, 1975-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 21-22)
  - Photography and Reproduction Invoices, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Robert Mann's Private Investigators, 1987-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Atthowe Fine Arts, 2001-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Hackett Freedman Gallery, 2003-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Reproduction Permission, 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Financial Information, 1949-1978, 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 28-30)
  - Miscellaneous, 1962-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 31-32)
- Scrapbooks, 1910-1994; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 10, 19
  Scrapbooks consist of a scrapbook related to exhibitions featuring Macdonald-Wright's works and scrapbooks of clipping.
  - Compiled Material, Exhibitions, Catalog Statements, and Reviews, 1913-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Exhibitions, 1952-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 34-35)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1910-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Scrapbook, 1954-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Printed Material, 1912-2002; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 10-12, 19
  Printed material includes a copy of Les Synchromistes exhibition catalog, a newspaper clipping, and The Future of Painting by Willard Wright. Artwork consists of blueprints for Macdonald-Wright's Synchrome Kineidoscope, a color and light projecting machine first envisioned by Macdonald-Wright and Morgan Russell as early as 1913 and finally completed in the late 1950s. Also included are newpaper and magazine clipping, exhibition announcements, and exhibition catalogs.
  - "Abstract & Surrealist Art in America" by Sidney Janis, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - American Art Review, 1974, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - "The Art of Stanton MacDonald-Wrght", 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Art Stuff Articles, 1942-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 40-41)
  - "A Treatise on Color", 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Auction Information, 2000-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Book Reference Material, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 45-46)
  - Bulletins, 1947-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Camera Work, 1912-1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - Clippings, 1929-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 4-12)
  - College Art Journal, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "Compendium a l'Usage des Artistes Peintres et de Amateurs Tableaux" by Jacques Blockx, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "Color, Myth, and Music" North Carolina Museum of Art, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - "Cubistes, Futuristes, Passeistes" by Gustave Coquiot, 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - "The Drawings of Hokusai", 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1948-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 18-22)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1947-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 23-33)
  - Exhibition Posters, 1953, 1964, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - "Focus on the Figure: Southern California Artists (1850-1950)", 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - "The Future of Painting" by Willard Huntington-Wright, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Japanese Publication, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - "Le Peintres Chinois" by Raphael Petrucci, circa 1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - "Les Synchromistes", 1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Magazines, 1949-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
  - "Manifeste des Pintres du Groupe: Les Artistes Musicalistes", 1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Michelangelo Buonarroti", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Morgan Russell, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 1950-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
  - "On the Philosophy of Aesthetics as Dictated to the Art Students League of Los Angeles", 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "Stanton MacDonald-Wright & Synchronism" by Will Sooth, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "Synchronism and Color Principles in American Painting, 1910-1930" and "Synchronism-The First American Movement" by William Agee, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Sculpture" by Joseph Goethe, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Selected Press Notices of Stanton MacDonald-Wright, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - "Ancient Art and Modern Man", 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Conservation Notebook, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "The John Quinn Collection of Paintings, Water Coors, Drawings, and Sculpture", 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Artwork, circa 1897-1970; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 12, 19
  Artwork consists of blueprints for Macdonald-Wright's Synchrome Kineidoscope, a color and light projecting machine that involved multiple projectors and film, and a sketchbook.
  - Childhood Drawings, circa 1897; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Color Wheel, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Kineidoscope Blueprints, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Drawings, 1897-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Drawings, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 22-23)
  - Sketches, circa 1955-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Woodblock Print, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Photographic Material, 1890-2004; Series 10; Archival Resource Key; 5.3 Linear feet Boxes 12-18, OV 20
  Photographic material consists of photographs of Stanton Macdonald-Wright and portraits and photographs of his family, Among these photographs is a glass plate negative of his family coat-of-arms. Also included are photographs, slides and transparencies of travels to Japan and Hawaii, and of Macdonald-Wright's artwork. There are also five glass plate images of some of MacDonald-Wright's paintings.
  Boxes 17 and 18 are primarily empty, labeled envelopes used to house the photographs of artwork. There are some individual slides and transparencies mixed in with the envelopes.
  - Family Photos, 1890-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 25-26)
  - Saunders Coat-of-Arms, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Glass Plates, Saunders Coat-of Arms and Miscellaneous Paintings, undated; Archival Resource Key; 6 Glass plate negatives
    There is one glass plate of the Saunders Coat-of-Arms which is either the original or duplicate for the photograph in the Saunders Coat-of-Arms file (12.27).
    There are five glass plates of some of MacDonald-Wright's paintings.
  - Stanton Macdonald-Wright by Jack Towers, circa 1960-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 28-29)
  - Stanton Macdonald-Wright, 1893-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 30-31)
  - Stanton & Jean Macdonald-Wright, circa 1956-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Stanton Macdonald-Wright and Other Individuals, 1932-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Personal, circa 1894-1960; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 20)
  - Personal, 1895-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 34-38)
  - Personal, circa 1930-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - "Color, Myth, and Music: Stanton MacDonald-Wright and Synchronism" Exhibition, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "Infidelity of Madame Lun", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Bellino Drive Mural, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Album, Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Artwork, circa 1955-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 11-24)
  - Artwork, circa 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1-17)
  - Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Album, Works of Art, 1959-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 3-5)
  - Album, Works of Art, circa 1910-1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Album, Works of Art, 1914-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Album, Works of Art, 1919-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Album, Works of Art, 1922-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Album, Works of Art, 1933-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Album, Works of Art, 1952-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Album, Works of Art, "Serenade in Blue", 1909-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Federal Art Project Murals, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Kineidoscope, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, Book Projects, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 15-18)
  - Contact Sheets, Book Project, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Morgan Russell Works of Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Slides, Japan Trip, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Slides, Japan Trip, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 1-3)
  - Slides, Hawaii, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 4-6)
  - Slides, Exhibition, Honolulu Academy of Art, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Slides, Yin Syn Summerfield, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Slides, House Gallery, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Slides, Gordon Water Colors, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Slides, Stessy, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Slides, Purveen Collection and Friend's Watercolors, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Slides, Retrospective, UCLA, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Slides, Morgan Russell, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Slides, Venice and Florence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Slides, Artwork, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 16-21)
  - Slides, Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Negatives, Mural, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - Negatives, Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 24-25)
  - Transparencies, Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 26-31)
  - Transparencies for Autobiography, 1912-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - Transparencies for Autobiography, 1956-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Transparencies, Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
  - Envelopes, Works of Art, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 5-8)
    Mostly empty manila envelopes used to store photos of artwork earlier in the series. Contains the title of the work, date, and dimensions on the front. There are some individual slides and transparencies mixed in with the envelopes.
  - Envelopes, Works of Art, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 1-4)